Register of the Hugh Anderson Moran papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Hugh Anderson Moran papers
1870-1946
1916-1933
48025
Hoover Institution Archives
5 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 1 oversize folder (3.6 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, clippings, maps, posters, and photographs relating to the Russian Civil War, political and economic conditions in Siberia and Manchuria, and relief work in Siberia and Manchuria, especially in the prisoner of war camps, during the Russian Civil War.
Moran, Hugh Anderson, 1881-1977.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1948.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Dr. Hugh Anderson Moran (1881-1977) graduated from Stanford University in 1905, and was the first athlete to receive the the prestigious Rhodes Scholarship. Moran was a member of the Delta Upsilon fraternity, president of the English Club, officer in the Young Men's Christian Association, and a member of the varsity track team.
Earning a doctorate in religion from Columbia University and Union Theological Seminary, Moran was ordained as a minister in the Presbyterian Church in 1908. He went on to serve as a Secretary of the International Committee of the Y.M.C.A. in China from 1909 to 1913. From 1916 to 1918, Moran was stationed in Vladivostok, Russia, in charge of prisoner of war relief in Siberia; he was also the special aide to Senator Elihu Root as part of the Special Diplomatic Mission in Russia in 1917.
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, writings, clippings, maps, posters, and photographs relating to the Russian Civil War, political and economic conditions in Siberia and Manchuria, and relief work in Siberia and Manchuria, especially in the prisoner of war camps, during the Russian Civil War.
Young Men's Christian associations.; International relief.; World War, 1914-1918--Russia.; World War, 1914-1918--War work.; Manchuria (China)--History.; Siberia (Russia)--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921--Civilian relief.; Soviet Union--History--Allied intervention, 1918-1920.
- Biographical File, 1916, 1918 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Passports
- Correspondence, 1916-1931, undated
  - Letters received, 1916-1917, undated
    - Margareta, Crown Princess of Sweden, 1916-1917 (Box-folder 1: 2-3)
    - Princess Lvov (Lwoff), circa 1917 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - General, 1916-1931, undated (Box-folder 1: 5-14)
    Letters from 1916 to 1918 begin with Moran entering Harbin, and contain accounts and daily activities of his station in Vladivostok. Correspondents include Governor David R. Francis, Dr. John R. Mott, A. C. Harte, Esq., Senator Elihu Root, J. A. Caldwell, Russell M. Story, and various Y.M.C.A. personnel stationed in Russia. Correspondence from 1919 to 1931 includes follow up on Moran's accounts in Russia, his personal life, and materials used in research pertaining to the Russian Civil War.
- Prisoner of War Records, 1916-1918
  - Receipts pertaining to prisoner of war supplies, 1916-1918 (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Reports and records pertaining to Y.M.C.A. secretaries working in Siberia, 1916-1917 (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - Records pertaining to daily activities, 1917 (Box-folder 1: 17)
- Writings, 1917-1931, undated
  - Timeline of events, 1917-1922 (Box-folder 1: 18)
    Contains an organized chart created by Moran; data focuses on major events and conflicts starting May 12, 1917, and ending November 14, 1922.
  - Manuscripts pertaining to Manchuria, 1931, undated (Box-folder 1: 19)
- Writings by Others, 1916-1939, undated
  - White Armies of Russia, by George Stewart, 1916-1933, undated
    Contains essays, letters, manuscript drafts, and reports that are written by Stewart and other contributors. Notes within the materials are provided by Moran.
    - Manuscript drafts, 1933 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Writing fragments, 1918-1926, undated (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - Appendices: 1 to 5, 1918-1920 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Appendices: A to C, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - Transcript of Milikukov's speech in the Russian Duma, circa 1916 (Box-folder 2: 5)
    - "The position Kept by France and Great Britain toward Fight against Bolsheviks in Russia,", circa 1920s (Box-folder 2: 6)
    - Letters to Josef Stalin and Leon Trotsky, 1933 (Box-folder 2: 7)
    - Sample dust cover, 1933 (Box-folder 2: 8)
    - Miscellaneous letters, 1920-1933 (Box-folder 2: 9)
      Contains a letter from Colonel Siroboyarsky, a representative of Ataman Semenoff, detailing his experience on the front line as a White Russian soldier and discussing the conditions of the soldiers and the civilians; and fan letters to Stewart following the release of his book.
  - Miscellaneous papers pertaining to the Russian Civil War, 1919-1939, undated (Box-folder 2: 10)
- Russian Military Maps, 1918-1919, undated (Box-folder 2: 11, Box-folder 6: 1-2, Map case)
- Drawing, circa 1919 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  Ink drawing of Russian soldier with horse in river.
- Printed Matter, 1870-1946, undated
  - Open letter to the Provisional Russian government, from President Woodrow Wilson, circa 1917 (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - Bulletin regarding the American Relief Administration (A.R.A.), 1918 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - Miscellaneous Russian bulletins, circa 1917-1921 (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - Stalin, Zinovyev Proclamation, circa 1919 (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - List of members of the Social Soviet Government, circa 1918 (Box-folder 2: 17)
  - Pamphlet, Pictures of Bolsheviks (1896 to 1919), circa 1920 (Box-folder 2: 18)
  - White Army propaganda posters (book fragments), circa 1918 (Box-folder 2: 19)
  - Propaganda posters, circa 1918 (Map case)
    Contains propaganda leaflets and a poster by Dmitry Stakhievich Orlov (Дмитрий Стахиевич Орлов).
  - Book fragments pertaining to leadership within the White Army, circa 1918-1921 (Box-folder 2: 20)
  - Book fragments pertaining to the Russian Civil War, circa 1920 (Box-folder 2: 21-28)
    Most pages contain contextual annotations, and translations by Moran.
  - Russian Armies in Exile, 1920 to 1923 (pamphlet translation), circa 1920s (Box-folder 2: 29)
  - Political cartoon clippings, 1920s (Box-folder 2: 30)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1920-1921 (Box-folder 6: 3-4)
    Contains full page rotogravures of Wrangel's troops (1920), and the Tsar's last photograph (1921) from the Chicago Sunday Tribune.
  - Newspaper clippings pertaining to Russia, 1918-1946, undated (Box-folder 3: 1-2)
  - Newspaper clippings pertaining to Manchuria, 1931-1932 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - League of Nations in Review, 1931 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Articles pertaining to the Soviet Union, 1930-1946 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Miscellaneous, 1870-1932 (Box-folder 3: 6)
    Includes lithographs of Russian landmarks, a copy of a letter from Dr. Chapman from Reverend Buchak regarding missionary work in Molodiatyn (1925), a report on the evangelical movement in Ukraine from the European Central Bureau for Church Relief Work (1927), and various clippings pertaining to religion in Ukraine.
- Currency, 1898-1922 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  Contains various Russian currency, including Tsar Nicholas II currency stamps (1915-1916), and Red and White Army currency.
- Photographs, circa 1913-1920, undated
  Most of the photographs contain annotations from Moran, or are series photographs from Underwood and Underwood.
  - Tsar Nicholas II, portrait, circa 1915 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Portrait of 12 year old Czech soldier, circa 1917 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Chinese Eastern Railway, circa 1917 (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Students from the University of Tonsk going back to Garda to relieve the Czechs, circa 1917 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - British Naval gunmen, H.M.S. Suffolk, circa 1917 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Russian churches and architecture, circa 1917 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - Russian frontier between Siberia and Mongolia, portrait of White Army soldier, circa 1917 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Americans at Vladivostok, circa 1917 (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Radola Gajada, circa 1917 (Box-folder 4: 9-10)
  - The army of the new provisional government at Harbin, Manchuria, circa 1917 (Box-folder 4: 11-13)
  - Grandmother of the revolution, Breshkovskaya, in her car at Vladivstok, circa 1917 (Box-folder 4: 14)
  - Military trucks at the front, circa 1917 (Box-folder 4: 15)
  - Churches in Russia, circa 1917 (Box-folder 4: 16)
  - Train in which Tsar Nicholas II abdicated, 1917 (Box-folder 4: 17-18)
  - Demonstration in Petrograd, 1917 (Box-folder 4: 19-20)
  - Mongols, May 1, 1917 in Tschita (Box-folder 4: 21)
  - Convicts from the prison in Tschita taking part in Labor Day parade, 1917 (Box-folder 4: 22)
  - Winter palace in Petrograd, 1917 (Box-folder 4: 23)
  - Cossack soldiers, 1917 (Box-folder 4: 24)
  - Beggars in Siberia, 1917 (Box-folder 4: 25)
  - Admiral Austin M. Knight, Vladivostok, 1917 (Box-folder 4: 26)
  - American railway engineers, 1917 (Box-folder 4: 27)
  - Senator Root, General Scott, Dr. Mott, 1917 (Box-folder 4: 28)
  - Ipatiev, house of Yekaterinburg, circa 1918 (Box-folder 4: 29)
  - Japanese officers visiting Russian athletic sports held at Harbin, by American Y.M.C.A., circa 1918 (Box-folder 4: 30)
  - Party of Americans escaping by way of Blagovestchensk, circa 1918 (Box-folder 4: 31)
  - Japanese loading artillery, circa 1918 (Box-folder 4: 32)
  - Parade of the 5th Siberian division, circa 1918 (Box-folder 4: 33)
  - Morgan Palmer with American relief workers escaping from Siberia, circa 1918 (Box-folder 4: 34)
  - Graves of German soldiers in Russian Poland, circa 1918 (Box-folder 4: 35)
  - Prisoners of war, circa 1918 (Box-folder 4: 36)
  - Russians waiting in a line for tea, circa 1918 (Box-folder 4: 37)
  - Market place, Vladivostok, circa 1918 (Box-folder 4: 38)
  - Eastern Mongols of Hailar, Mongolia, circa 1918 (Box-folder 4: 39-42)
  - Station Harbin, Manchuria, circa 1918 (Box-folder 4: 43-47)
  - Bohdan Pavlu, circa 1918 (Box-folder 4: 48)
  - General Jan Syrovy, circa 1918 (Box-folder 4: 49)
  - Military procession going to church to pray for victory, circa 1918 (Box-folder 4: 50)
  - Czech soldier who threw a hand grenade at Bolshevik headquarters, 1918 (Box-folder 4: 51)
  - Allied naval officers, 1918 (Box-folder 4: 52)
  - Czech soldiers, Vladivostok, 1918 (Box-folder 4: 53)
  - American expeditionary forces, Siberian train, circa 1919 (Box-folder 4: 54)
  - Russian soldiers returning home, circa 1919 (Box-folder 4: 55)
  - Imperial Russian family portrait, circa 1913 (Box-folder 4: 56)
  - Cossack soldiers, 1917 (Box-folder 4: 57)
  - Convicts from the prison in Tschita taking part in Labor Day parade, 1917 (Box-folder 4: 58)
  - Kerensky as head of provisional government, 1917 (Box-folder 4: 59)
  - Milan Stefanik, portrait, 1917 (Box-folder 4: 60)
  - Russian White Army soldiers, 1917-1919 (Boxes 4-5)
  - American commanders, 1917-1920 (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - Carvings by a German soldier in Siberia, circa 1918 (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - Prisoner of war camps, circa 1918 (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - Surgeons of Allied forces, circa 1918 (Box-folder 5: 7)
  - Ukrainian army prepares to fight Bolsheviks, 1918 (Box-folder 5: 8)
  - Refugees in Russia, 1918-1919, undated (Box-folder 5: 9)
  - Fighting Finnish against Bolshevik army, 1918 (Box-folder 5: 10)
  - Russian White Army women soldiers, 1918 (Box-folder 5: 11)
  - American troops in Russia, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 5: 12)
  - Admiral Kolchak's troops in the UFA, 1919 (Box-folder 5: 13-18)
  - American Red Cross, Vladivostok, 1919 (Box-folder 5: 19)
  - General Otani in Siberia, 1919 (Box-folder 5: 20)
  - Japanese train in Siberia, 1919 (Box-folder 5: 21)
  - Trotsky and Lenin speaking in Red Square, circa 1919 (Box-folder 5: 22)
  - Lenin speaking in Red Square, circa 1919 (Box-folder 5: 23)
  - American expeditionary forces, 1919 (Box-folder 5: 24)
  - Kirilenko at Kronstadt, 1919 (Box-folder 5: 25)
  - Czechoslovakian troops, 1919-1920, undated (Box-folder 5: 26)
  - Russian White Army commanders, 1919-1920, undated (Box-folder 5: 27)
  - Bolshevik army troops, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 5: 28-30)
  - American troops in Russia, 1920 (Box-folder 5: 31)
  - Estonian liberation war, 1920 (Box-folder 5: 32)
  - Defeat of Wrangel, 1920 (Box-folder 5: 33)